Finding Aid for the Ezra Pound Papers, 1911-1949
UCLA Library, Department of Special Collections
Ezra Pound Papers,
1911-1949
636
Pound, Ezra, 1885-1972
2 boxes (1.0 linear ft.)
University of California, Los Angeles. Library. Department of Special Collections. Los Angeles, California 90095-1575
Ezra Pound (1885-1972) was a poet, translator, and a representative for Poetry magazine, and The little review. His published works include A lume spento (1908), Homage to Sextus Propertius (1917), and Hugh Selwyn Mauberly (1920). The collection contains Pound's correspondence with E.W. Titus, letters to various persons, corrected proofs of poems, typescripts, and issues of The Pound newsletter.
Administrative Information
Restrictions on Access
COLLECTION STORED OFF-SITE AT SRLF: Advance notice required for access.
Additional Physical Form Available
A copy of the original version of this online finding aid is available at the UCLA Department of Special Collections for in-house consultation and may be obtained for a fee. Please contact:
Public Services Division
UCLA Library, Department of Special Collections
Room A1713, Charles E. Young Research Library
Box 951575
Los Angeles, CA 90095-1575
Telephone: 310/825-4988 (10:00 a.m. - 4:45 p.m., Pacific Time)
Email: spec-coll@library.ucla.edu
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 4233609
Biography
Pound was born in Hailey, Idaho on October 30, 1885; attended the University of Pennsylvania and Hamilton College; taught romance philology at Wabash College; left for Europe; in 1908 his first book of verse, A lume spento, was published; lived in London from 1908-20, where he published translations of Italian and Provençal poetry and adaptations from Chinese poems; published Homage to Sextus Propertius (1917) and Hugh Selwyn Mauberly (1920); served as London representative for Poetry magazine, and for The little review; began to write The cantos, the first of which was published in 1925; moved to Paris in 1920, and to Rapallo, Italy five years later; made pro-Fascist broadcasts from Italy after the U.S. declared war; was indicted for treason, held at a detention center in Pisa in 1945, and was transferred to St. Elizabeth's Hospital for the criminally insane in Washington, D.C. in 1946; awarded the Bollingen Prize for poetry in 1949; returned to Italy after his release in 1958; he died in Venice on November 1, 1972.
Scope and Content
Collection contains Pound correspondence with E.W. Titus, letters to various persons, corrected proofs of poems published in The little review, proofs of Certain noble plays of Japan with holograph corrections, typescript drafts of cantos xii and xiii, typescripts of the Noh stories, Moon madness and The rabbit's house, and ephemera. Also contains numbers 1-10 of The Pound newsletter and two reels of microfilm containing If this be treason... [n.p., c.1948] and The cantos of Ezra Pound.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Pound, Ezra, 1885-1972--Archives.; Poets, American--20th century--Archival resources.; Microfilms.
Container List
- Pound, Ezra. A Lume Spento., Bound in green morocco. (Box 1)
  Proofs revised by the author. Given to D.H. Lawrence about 1911.
- ----. Cantos XII and XIII., 10 leaves. Typescript with holograph corrections. In a black cloth case. (Box 1)
- ----. Demarcations and The Revolution Betrayed. in the British Union Quarterly, vol.1 no.1 and vol.2 no.1. January-April 1937 and January-March 1938. (Box 1)
  E. Pound's contributions.
- ----. Certain Noble Plays of Japan. Churchtown, Dundrum: The Cuala Press. 1916., Proof sheets with copious holograph corrections. In a blue morocco slipcase. (Box 1)
- ----. Certain Noble Plays of Japan. Churchtown, Dundrum: The Cuala Press. 1916., Photocopy. (Box 1)
- ---- Letters to E.W. Titus. Rapallo. 1927-1930., 11 items (21 leaves). Typescript and holograph. (Box 1)
- ---- Miscellaneous letters to various persons: (Box 1)
  4 letters to Alfred Fowler, Editory of The Miscellany, Kansas City. London, ca. 1915 (9 leaves. Typescript and holograph).
  1 letter to George S. Fraser. [Washington?] ca. 1949 (3 leaves. Typescript and holograph).
  1 letter to Donald Pearce. Washington, December 6, 1953 (1 leaf. Typescript).
  1 letter to Derek Stanford. Washington, January 15, 1949 (1 leaf. Holograph).
  1 letter to Dear Sir. Venice, June 26, 1927 (2 leaves. Holograph).
- ----. The Little Review. May 1918. vol.6 no.1., Holograph corrections, pp.19-30. (Box 1)
- ----. Moon Madness. Translation. n.p. n.d, 2 leaves. 31 × 21cm. Typescript with holograph corrections in pencil. (Box 1)
  A Noh story translated from the Japanese. Original title: The Moon Faun. Printed in Miscellany, ca. 1915, published by the American Book Plate Society, 1914-1916.
  Gift of Willard Hougland, August 1958.
- ----. The Rabbits' House. Translation. n.p. n.d, 2 leaves. 31 × 21cm. Typescript with holograph corrections in pencil. (Box 1)
  A Noh story translated from the Japanese. Printed in Miscellany, ca. 1915, published by the American Book Plate Society, 1914-1916.
- Fraser, George Sutherland, 1915-. News from South America. London: Harvill Press. 1949. (Box 1)
  Presentation copy from George S. Fraser[?] to John Gawsworth [pseudonym for Terence Ian Fytton Armstrong] with Ezra Pound's comments, taken from an original letter from Pound to Fraser, copied on relevant pages by Fraser[?].
  For this letter, SEE: Letters, signed, to various persons.
  Ex libris: C.K. Ogden.
- Letters, signed, to various persons, v.p. v.d., 7 pieces. (Box 1)
  1 letter to Derek Stanford, January 17, 1949.
  1 letter to Donald Pearce, December 6, 1953.
  4 letters to Alfred Fowler, ca. 1915.
  1 letter to George S. Fraser, ca. 1949.
- Ephemera. v.p. v.d., 6 items. (Box 1)
- The Pound Newsletter, no.1-10. (Box 2)
- If this be treason..., n.p., c. 1948., 33pp. 1 reel of microfilm. (Box 2)
  Contents: E.E. Cummings/examined. - James Joyce: to his memory. - A french accent. - Canto 45. - Blast. Limited edition, copy no.21.
- The Cantos of Ezra Pound. New York: Farrar and Rinehart, c. 1933., 22, [1]p. 1 reel of microfilm. (Box 2)
  Some testimonies by Ernest Hemingway, Ford Madox Ford, T.S. Eliot, Hugh Walpole, Archibald MacLeish, James Joyce, and others.
Related Material
Jaime de Angulo Papers (Collection 160). Available at Department of Special Collections, UCLA.
(Letters to de Angulo in Box 2).
Earl Roy Miner Papers (Collection 821). Available at Department of Special Collections, UCLA.
(Letters to Miner in Box 1).
Harold Monro Papers (Collection 745). Available at Department of Special Collections, UCLA.
(Letters to Monro in Box 2).
Miscellaneous Manuscripts Collection (Collection 100). Available at Department of Special Collections, UCLA.
(Letters to Frederic Manning in Box 101).
(Letter to Cyril M. Schneider about Nathaniel West in Box 36).
Peter Russell Papers (Collection 921). Available at Department of Special Collections, UCLA.
(Letters to Edgar Jepson, and E. Pound ephemera in Box 1).